Hello, good
morning. Today's דף daf is ערכין Erchin דף daf י"ח yud chet
and we will pick up near the bottom on י"ז עמוד ב'.
yud zayin amud bais. So just to refresh our memory what we're
up to, the משנה Mishnah was talking about the דין din in
ערכין Erchin that, you know, the תורה Torah normally gives a fixed
amount when you say you're, you know, someone's you're going to donate
to the מקדש Mikdash someone's ערך. erech. So the תורה Torah tells
you for this age it's this amount, for this age it's this
amount. And then it says but if you're too poor to afford
that, so the כהן Kohen assesses how much you can afford and
there was a מחלוקת machlokes in the משנה Mishnah at what point
do you have to be poor to get that special discount.
The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma said
if you are you have to be poor both at the time
you make the ערך erech and at the time you're paying the
ערך. erech. And רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said that you have to
be poor for the entire interval from the time you make it
until the time you pay it in order to get that discount.
And the גמרא Gemara is discussing
where's the source for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
So the גמרא Gemara suggests that the source is the word והוא
vehu and the word והוא vehu somehow teaches us that it applies
to the entire interval. So now the גמרא Gemara is going through
every other case of that we have the word והוא vehu in
the תורה Torah and asks if indeed רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
say there also that it implies to the entire interval. So
the case we are discussing now
is י"ז עמוד ב', yud zayin amud bais, six lines from the
bottom, second word. We're going to start אלא מעתה והוא עד
עד
שיהא
כשר מתחילתו ועד סופו.
ela me'ata vehu ed ad sheyehei
kosher mitechilaso ve'ad sofo. So this is talking about שבועת העדות. shvuas
ha'edus. If
I claim that you know some information that would help me in
a court case I have and you deny knowing any such information,
so I could make you take a שבועה, shvua, I could make
you take an oath that you don't in fact know anything. So
I can only make you take that oath if you are in
fact a כשר kosher witness.
So the גמרא Gemara asks if רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks that
והוא vehu always means the entire interval in the case of שבועת
העדות shvuas ha'edus would he say that to make you take that
שבועה shvua you have to be a כשר kosher witness from the
entire time from when you allegedly witnessed the event I'm claiming you
witnessed until the time that you would the date of my court
case that you would give that testimony in court. אלא מעתה והוא
עד עד שיהא כשר מתחילתו ועד סופו ela me'ata vehu ed ad
sheyehei kosher mitechilaso ve'ad sofo וכי
תימא הכא נמי vechi teima hacha nami if you would say yeah
okay רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda does hold that. והתניא vehatanya but don't
we have a ברייתא braisa היה יודע לו בעדות עד שלא נעשה
חתנו ונעשה חתנו. haya yode'a lo be'edus ad shelo na'asa chosno vena'asa
chosno.
So if he knew a certain if you're claiming he knew some
testimony
before he was your son-in-law
and then he became your son-in-law, i.e. he married your daughter, that's
a way to make him פסול לעדות, posul le'edus, make him a
not כשר עד kosher ed, at least for this particular case.
פקח ונתחרש pike'ach venis-charesh or he was he had all of his
faculties of hearing and speech and then he became a deaf-mute who
is פסול לעדות. posul le'edus. פתוח ונסתמא patu'ach venistama or he could
see and he became blind. רש"י Rashi says there's a special גזירת
הכתוב gezeiras hakasuv או ראה o ra'ah that a blind person is
פסול
לעדות. posul le'edus.
שפוי ונשתטה shafui venishtateh or he was sane and he became crazy.
הרי זה פסול. harei zeh posul.
So in each of these cases so you can't make the person
take a שבועת העדות shvuas ha'edus so that works well so far.
אבל aval היה יודע לו עדות עד שלא נעשה חתנו ונעשה חתנו
ואחר כך
מתה בתו. haya yode'a lo edus ad shelo na'asa chosno vena'asa chosno
ve'achar kach mesa bito.
So however what's the case where he wasn't your
son-in-law at the time of the event he's alleged to have witnessed,
then he marries your daughter, he becomes your son-in-law, then your daughter
dies and he is no longer your son-in-law, he's כשר לעדות kosher
le'edus again. So he is a כשר kosher עד ed both at
the time he saw the event and at the time he would
have to give testimony in court. He just had this period in
the middle where he wasn't. So allegedly according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda he wasn't כשר kosher for the entire interval that shouldn't be
good. Or
analogously פקח ונתחרש
וחזר
ונתפקח pike'ach venis-charesh vechazar venispake'ach or he could hear and speak and
then he became a deaf-mute and then he was able to hear
and speak again. פתוח ונסתמא ואחר כך נתפתח patu'ach venistama ve'achar kach
nispate'ach or he
was he could see and then he went blind and then he
was able to see again. שפוי ונשתטה וחזר ונשתפה shafui venishtateh vechazar
venishtapeh or he was sane and became crazy and became sane again.
In each of these cases כשר. kosher Problem for רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda the ברייתא braisa says that if you just had a period
in the middle when you weren't כשר kosher. as long as you
were a כשר kosher עד ed both at the beginning and at
the end that's good you can make the person take a שבועת
העדות. shvuas ha'edus. זה
הכלל zeh haklal the ברייתא braisa gives us כל שתחילתו. kol shetechilaso.
So וסופו בכשרות, v'sofo b'kashrus, anytime the beginning and the end he's
a כשר kosher עד, ed כשר. kosher.
So this seems to be a problem for רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's
שיטה, shitta, but the גמרא Gemara says it's not a problem, שאני
התם, shani hatam, דאמר קרא, d'amar kra, או ראה או לא יגיד.
o ra'ah o lo yagid. So we kind of take the proper
punctuation out of the פסוק, pasuk, read it as or he saw,
in the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk it would be, you
know, period, אם לא יגיד, im lo yagid, if he then does
not tell, but we read it all together, או ראה אם לא
יגיד. o ra'ah im lo yagid. בראיה והגדה תלה רחמנא מילתא. B're'iyah
v'hagadah talah rachmana milta.
So we have a special גזירת הכתוב gzeiras hakasuv by שבועת העדות
shvuas ha'aidus that the only periods that are important are ראיה re'iyah
when he saw the event and הגדה hagadah when he would give
the testimony in court. So you can't prove anything about the word
והוא v'hu in general from שבועת העדות. shvuas ha'aidus. בראיה והגדה תלה
מילתא והאיכא, B're'iyah v'hagadah talah milta v'ha'ika, and in this
and we have in our case we have both ראיה re'iyah and
הגדה. hagadah. ואלא והוא למה לי? V'ela v'hu lama li?
So if we learn if we learn that out from this, so
why do we need the word והוא v'hu at all by
שבועת העדות? shvuas ha'aidus? לכדתניא, L'chidetanya, for another another הלכה halacha that
we learn from the following ברייתא. braisa. ראה סיעה של בני אדם
עומדים ועד בתוכם. Ra'ah si'ah shel bnei adam omdim v'ed betocham.
So if you see this large company of people and you know
that your witnesses are among them, ואמר משביעני עליכם אם אתם יודעים
לי עדות, v'amar mashbi'ani aleichem im atem yodim li eidus,
he says I make all of you take an oath that none
of you that none of you know testimony for me, שתבואו ותעידוני,
shetavou v'sa'iduni, that
that if you know testimony for me you should come and give
the testimony. יכול יהיה חייב? Yachol yihiyeh chayav? I might have thought
even in that case they would be חייב chayav either to give
the testimony or to take the oath that they don't know anything.
תלמוד לומר והוא עד והרי לא ייחד עדו. Talmud lomar v'hu ed
v'harei lo yicheid ado.
והוא V'hu teaches that you have to specify the exact person that
you're claiming knows testimony for you and it's not enough to just
go to a whole group of people and say any of you
or all of you. יכול אפילו אמר כל מי? Yachol afilu amar
kol mi?
So now the גמרא Gemara says maybe I would think even if
you say the first case you said I'm משביע, mashbi'a,
I want I'm claiming I want the whole group as one
and you said all of you either have to take a testimony
take an oath that you don't know anything or come and give
the testimony. It says I might have thought even if you said
כל מי kol mi rather than all of you but any of
you, any one of you, I might have thought that's also called
not specifying your your witnesses. תלמוד לומר והוא עד
והרי ייחד עדו.
Talmud lomar v'hu ed
v'harei yicheid ado. And somehow the גמרא Gemara says somehow the word
עד ed after והוא v'hu teaches us that it's sufficient to say
any as long as you're not implying the whole group even if
you don't call them out by name.
Isn't there an obligation to testify
if they have עדות eidus on if they saw something, they are
an עד ed for him? Yeah. So whether he singles them out
or it's
apart from all of that, it's their own personal...
It is their obligation, but he's he's claiming that they're not fulfilling
their obligation. That's that's the case.
He's he's saying you know testimony for me and you're not coming
forward and the person's claiming I don't know anything. And therefore he
said and in that case he can make them take an oath
that he doesn't know anything.
But he can't make the whole group take an oath.
Right.
Is it a שבועת שוא shvuas shav or is it a...
It's a it's a שבועת העדות. shvuas ha'aidus.
It's a שבועת העדות shvuas ha'aidus and שבועת שוא shvuas shav is
different. שבועת שוא... shvuas shav...
I mean a שבועת שוא shvuas shav could be any שבועת שוא,
shvuas shav, it's just when you take a false oath.
Oh, that's a very good point, a person
initiates the oath but he's not forced to by situation.
Right.
Okay. So moving on, אבל בקרבנות אינו כן. aval b'korbanos eino kein.
So that's going back to the משנה. mishna. So the דין din
that we said that to get the poor person's discount you have
to either according to the תנא קמא tanna kamma be poor both
at the beginning and at the end or according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda for the whole interval. So that only applies to ערכין.
erchin. So the משנה mishna said that doesn't בקרבנות אינו כן, b'korbanos
eino kein, that doesn't apply to קרבנות, korbanos, specifically this is talking
about קרבן מצורע korban metzora because that's the only קרבן korban that
has a
tiered
schedule, the קרבן עולה ויורד korban oleh v'yored that you give a
different קרבן korban if you're richer or if you're poor. So he's
saying that goes only according to the time that when you're giving
it. It doesn't you don't look at beginning and intervals.
And the the example in the משנה mishna was מת אביו והניח
לו ריבוא. meis aviv v'hiniach lo ribo. So if your if your
father died and left you tens of thousands of something, או ספינתו
בים ובא לו בריבואות, o sfinaso bayam uva lo b'ribuos, or you
have a boat at sea with thousands of something, it doesn't specify
a unit, אין להקדש בהם כלום. ein l'hekdesh bahem klum. So that
doesn't count towards the assessment of how wealthy you are. So the
גמרא Gemara so moving on to the דף, daf, the גמרא Gemara
asks, אביב מת והניח לו ריבוא? aviv meis v'hiniach lo ribo? "אמר
רב פפא" Amar Rav Papa Correct. "אימא מניח לו" eima maniach lo
Correct. "גמרא" Gemara Correct. "פשיטא" pshita Correct. "כשהיה אביו גוסס" keshehaya aviv
goses Correct. "מהו דתימא" mahu deteima Correct. "רוב גוססין למיתה" rov gosesin
lemita Correct. "כל גוססין למיתה" kol gosesin lemita Correct. "גוסס" goses Correct.
"קא משמע לן" ka mashma lan Correct. "ספינה שבים ובא לו בריבואות"
sfina shebayam uva lo beribuot Correct. "עשיר הוא" ashir hu Correct. "אמר
רב חסדא" Amar Rav Chisda Correct. "כשהיתה מוכרת ומושכרת" keshehaita mucheret umuscheret
Correct. "ומושכרת ליד אחרים" umuscheret leyad acherim Correct. "והאיכא שכירות" veha ika
schirut Correct. "שכירות אינה משתלמת אלא לבסוף" schirut eina mishtalemet ela levasof
Correct. "קרבן מצורע" korban metzora Correct. "הלכה" halacha Correct. "ישנה לשכירות מתחילה
ועד סוף" yeshna lischirut mitechila ve'ad sof Correct. "מחלוקת" machloket Correct. "גמרות"
Gemarot Correct. "נפקא מינה" nafka mina Correct. "וטיפוק ליה משום ספינה" vetipok
lei mishum sfina Correct. "אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Papa, אימא מניח
לו. eima maniach lo. No, no, it's not that. It's not that
your father already died and left you the money, it's that your
father's wealthy and when he dies, you know, after 120 years, he'll
leave you the money.
So the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא. pshita. Isn't that, isn't that obvious
that you don't have the money now? Your father's wealthy, but you're
not wealthy.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, what's the case we're talking about?
כשהיה אביו גוסס, keshehaya aviv goses, when your father is dying. מהו
דתימא, mahu deteima, what would I have thought? רוב גוססין למיתה, rov
gosesin lemita, since most people who are in this, this is like
the last throes of death when you're almost certainly going to die,
it's almost an understatement when the גמרא Gemara says רוב גוססין למיתה,
rov gosesin lemita, כל גוססין למיתה. kol gosesin lemita. The definition of
a גוסס goses is someone who by all medical knowledge is irreversibly
going to die within the next three days.
So
since we know this person is, is imminently going to die, we
might have thought that you should count the inheritance as if it
were yours already. קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, we don't. We
still count only what you have in your possession right now.
So the גמרא Gemara moves on to the second case: ספינה שבים
ובא לו בריבואות. sfina shebayam uva lo beribuot.
So if you have a boat at sea that has tens of
thousands of dollars on it, עשיר הוא? ashir hu? And again the
גמרא Gemara asks the same question: What do you mean? You're, you're
wealthy. So what that your boat's at sea?
אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav
Chisda, כשהיתה מוכרת
ומושכרת.
keshehaita
mucheret umuscheret.
No, you don't actually have any property on the boat. The boat
is rented out, and what are the tens of thousands we're talking
about? The tens of thousands we're talking about are the tens of
thousands that people are paying you in rental fees for the boat.
So not only do you not have access to it, but you
don't actually have any money on it. ומושכרת ליד אחרים. umuscheret leyad
acherim. והאיכא שכירות? veha ika schirut?
So the גמרא Gemara asks, but wait a second, you have the
rental fee. Doesn't, isn't that enough to make you wealthy? So the
גמרא Gemara says שכירות אינה משתלמת אלא לבסוף. schirut eina mishtalemet ela
levasof. So the, the way, the way their contracts worked back then
is when you rented out a boat, apparently you didn't pay the
rental fee until, you'd rent it out for a whole year, you
wouldn't pay the rental fee until the end of the year. So
right now you don't have the money. At the end of the
year, at the end of the year you'll, you'll have all that
money in rental fees for the boat. But,
but right now you don't. So if you're, if you're bringing your
קרבן מצורע korban metzora right now, we assess you only based on
what you have right now.
Well, it really shouldn't make a difference שכירות אינה משתלמת אלא לבסוף,
schirut eina mishtalemet ela levasof, because let's say they owed it to
you in the beginning and they haven't paid you yet.
You still wouldn't be considered wealthy, would you be? If you didn't,
if you don't have the money because they didn't, they owe it
to you, let's say.
If he, right, but I could take him to court and get
it right now.
No, you can't. I mean, you could take him to court, but
until the, the court case and until they judge in your favor,
there has to be a, you know, it's not like you're going
to get it tomorrow, today.
Right, I'm not sure if, if you have money that is legally
obligated to you right now and it is, you know, in theory
actionable right now, I'm not sure what the הלכה halacha would be
in that case, if we would, if we would look at what's
actually physically in your possession or what you could theoretically get. So
I'm, I'm not sure what the הלכה halacha is in that case.
But anyway, some would say ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף. yeshna lischirut
mitechila ve'ad sof. That's a מחלוקת machloket itself too.
So this is going according to that opinion that says that שכירות
אינה משתלמת אלא לבסוף, schirut eina mishtalemet ela levasof, but that's not
necessarily all, you know, agreed upon, right? Yeah, we've seen, we've seen
in other places in גמרות Gemarot that, you know, they kind of
accrue the whole way.
That you have to pay the whole way? I mean, I think
I, I recall that מחלוקת, machloket, but I don't, I don't recall
a מחלוקת machloket about when you have to pay. Okay, but there's,
there's other נפקא מינהs nafka mina of
that מחלוקת, machloket, so let's, you know, my, the rest of it
is, to me it would seem that it depends what money you
have, you know, in your pocket so to speak.
Right, I'm, again, I'm, I'm not sure. I mean, it's, it's not
the same case. So the case where it's actionable right now versus
the case where I couldn't even try and get it until the
end of the year, that, so it's, it's not the same case,
but that middle case where it is actionable right now but you
don't have it right now, I'm not sure what the הלכה halacha
would be in that case.
Yeah, and let's say I do have all of it, but it's
hypothecated to somebody else because like, you know, because I took out
a ten thousand dollar loan, you know, and I have to pay
him next year. You know what I mean? Does that make, does
that count? Let's, you know, let's say I have a hundred thousand,
but I have to pay it all to you, you know, the
reverse case, right? This, you know, like I, I'm renting your boat,
you know, so would that mean that like, although I have to
pay you next year, I have a hundred thousand dollars now, so
I'm considered wealthy even though like, you know, tomorrow it'll be gone?
Well, it's the end of the year tomorrow, let's say.
I mean, it might be. I mean, your obligation to pay this
one comes first, so I would assume that, I would assume that
yeah, you pay that and when, when the other, when the other
debt comes due, we'll worry about that one in its time.
Okay, so going on, so then the גמרא Gemara asks: וטיפוק ליה
משום ספינה? vetipok lei mishum sfina? So what about the value of
the boat itself?
So there's, there's actually, there's a case where the boat is rented
out, right? You don't in theory have access to the boat, but
you still own it. You still have title on the boat. So
we should say we should call you wealthy based on the fact
that you own this boat.
So the גמרא Gemara says..." "אמר רב פפא" Amar Rav Papa Correct.
"אימא מניח לו" eima maniach lo Correct. "גמרא" Gemara Correct. "פשיטא" pshita
Correct. So הא מני, ha mani, so who's the author of our
משנה? Mishnah? רבי אליעזר היא. Rabbi Eliezer hi. דתנן רבי אליעזר אומר
אם היה איכר נותן לו צמדו וחמור נותן לו חמורו. ditnan Rabbi
Eliezer omer im haya ikar noten lo tzimdo ve-chamor noten lo chamoro.
So there's a משנה Mishnah later on in the מסכת masechet that
says Rabbi Eliezer says when we're assessing how wealthy you are for
the purpose for these purposes,
if you are a farmer, we don't we don't take away
your utensils, your cattle. What's the word for a pair of cattle?
A
herd.
We don't
take away your herd, whatever.
Yeah, whatever the cattle that you plow your field with.
If you're a farmer, we don't take away the cattle that you
plow your field with, and if you are a חמר, chammar, if
you're a donkey driver, we don't take away your donkey. So Rabbi
Eliezer has this שיטה shittah that when we
are when we are assessing how wealthy you are for the purposes
of of bringing this קרבן, korban, basically we don't take away your
פרנסה. parnassah. We don't take away the main things that you earn
a living with. That doesn't count.
That would mean though, like let's say I have no liquid assets
and all my assets are in real estate in other countries, I'd
be considered wealthy even though I don't, you know, have much in
my bank account.
In theory, yeah.
That's not theory, practically for this. That means I would, you know,
I mean it doesn't explicitly discuss that case, but that that would
seem to be the implication. Yes.
It says that he does give him אם היה איכר נותן. im
haya ikar noten.
Right, no, but I'm no.
נותן לו noten lo meaning the כהן kohen leaves it for the
guy.
נותן noten gives it back to him.
We leave it for him. This is talking about somebody who made
a נדר, neder, who made who said I'll give this such and
such the value of something to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, right? If he says it if he doesn't
have it, why isn't he liable? Can't we assume he knows what
he's worth? And
if somebody says it makes a donation,
we assume he knows the תורה Torah also that says a poor
person can can give less in that case.
If I'm in shul and they're having an appeal, I make a
huge donation, that's a then I'm obligated to pay. Do I have
the right to say oh sorry, I don't have four million dollars,
I'm sorry?
No, unless there's a specific clause in the rules that that make
that exception, which the תורה Torah does in the case of ערכין.
Erchin.
So here we're saying basically people can make any kind of נדר
neder and
no, it doesn't apply to most נדרים. nedarim. It applies only to
ערכין. Erchin.
This type of this type of
נדר, neder, yeah.
So it's we're not taking it that seriously. You can say it
and then we take the כהן's kohen time to come and figure
out how much you're worth and
if you can't pay, okay, we'll forget about it.
Right.
Yeah, but also, you know, don't forget this can also be this
type of thing where, you know, you might have been rich at
the time and then you made a נדר neder but then, you
know, then everything else went up in flames, you know, we're talking
about by the time you actually go to give it, your circumstances
change. That's a whole משנה Mishnah too. עני והעשיר, ani ve-he-ashir, you
know, that whole thing.
So if you do, you know, obligate you
this and which you would have known, but you're taking it very
lightly and it's not considered like a vow or any type of
obligation.
Right, ערכין Erchin is its own special category with its own special
rules that doesn't really fit the rest of נדרים.
nedarim. Right, all this is on קרבנות korbanot though.
Right, and קרבן מצורע, korban metzora, yeah. The two the two areas
in הלכה halachah where we have special where we have special exemptions
for poor people are ערכין Erchin and קרבן מצורע. korban metzora.
Okay, so the משנה. Mishnah. So the משנה Mishnah says השנים בנדר
כיצד. hashanim be-neder keitzad. So the the first משנה Mishnah told us
this rule that when we are so ערכין Erchin have different prices
based on how old the person you are מעריך ma'arich is. So
the
the משנה Mishnah in the first משנה Mishnah said the when determining
the age, it goes based on the person whose value you are
being מעריך, ma'arich, not on the person who is giving it, which
seems obvious. Yeah, does seem obvious, but so so the משנה Mishnah
here now is כיצד. keitzad. So what's the case? ילד שהעריך זקן.
yeled she-he'erich zaken. So ילד yeled here doesn't mean a child, it
means it means an adult as opposed to
a younger adult.
Right, a younger adult, someone between twenty and sixty as opposed to
a זקן zaken who is someone over sixty.
So a ילד yeled who who promises the ערך erech of a
זקן, zaken, נותן ערך זקן. noten erech zaken. He he gives the
he gives the price for the זקן. zaken. וזקן שהעריך את הילד,
ve-zaken she-he'erich et ha-yeled, and if a זקן zaken promises the ערך
erech of a ילד, yeled, נותן ערך ילד. noten erech yeled. He
gives the he gives the price for the ילד. yeled. So the
next case in the משנה Mishnah was הערכין בנערך כיצד. ha-erchin be-ne'erach
keitzad. So the ערכין erchin go according to the one who is
being נערך, ne'erach, the one whose value was promised. So what's the
case? איש שהעריך את האשה. ish she-he'erich et ha-ishah. So if a
man promises the ערך erech of a woman, נותן ערך אשה. noten
erech ishah. He gives the price for a woman. ואשה שהעריכה איש,
ve-ishah she-he'erichah ish, if a woman promises the ערך erech of a
man, נותן ערך איש. noten erech ish. She gives the she gives
the price for a man. והערך בזמן הערך כיצד. ve-ha-erech bi-zman ha-erech
keitzad. So the next case in the משנה Mishnah was the ערך
erech follows the time that you made the the ערך, erech, not
the time that
you... So if you, if you made, if you made the vow,
if you made the ערך erech when the person who you were
evaluating was still less than five years old and before you gave
it they became five years old,
or
בן חמש פחות מבן עשרים, ben chamesh pachot miben esrim, or they
were, or they were above five and less than twenty ונעשה יתר
על בן עשרים, vena'aseh yater al ben esrim, or they and then
before you gave it they became over twenty years old, so each
one of those would change the value that you'd have to give,
נותן בזמן הערך. noten bizman ha-erech. So you give based on the
time you made the ערך erech not at the time you're giving
it.
So now the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara says תנו רבנן, tano
rabanan, so we quote a ברייתא, braita, הקיש דמים לערכין. atkeish damim
l'erchin. So we had,
we had a היקש hekesh earlier in the מסכת masechet or later
in the מסכת, masechet, no, later in the מסכת. masechet. We have
a היקש hekesh between ערכין erchin and דמים damim which in this
case refers to other sorts of נדרים, nedarim, other sorts of things
you can promise.
So
for what, for what purpose did we have that? בין מרגלית לקלים
ולידון בכבודו. bin margalit l'kalim v'lidon b'chvodo. So when, when we are
making you sell property to fulfill some sort of נדר neder that
you took, so we don't make you מרגלית לקלים margalit l'kalim means
we sell it, we sell, we sell your property the easiest way
possible. We don't make you go into the city even though you
might be able to sell it for a higher value there. You
can sell it right here for whatever it's worth right here.
How do you translate that? What is מרגלית לקלים?
margalit l'kalim? מרגלית margalit is a pearl. לקלים l'kalim is the easiest
way.
But what does a pearl have to do with this?
If you own a מרגלית margalit and we're making you sell it
to pay your נדר, neder, you sell it the easiest way possible.
It has a very concrete value.
Is that only because it's a מרגלית margalit because it's מטלטלין metaltelin
or we mean any property? But let's say it's real estate, do
I have to go to the city then and sell it?
I think any property. Okay.
Because
with a מרגלית margalit you might get more in the city because
people want pearls.
Right. That, the assumption is, the assumption is you will get, the
assumption is you will get more in the city but you don't
have to do that. We let you sell it in the easiest
way possible. ולידון בכבודו. v'lidon b'chvodo. So that is this דין din
so רש"י Rashi says שאם העריך דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו כגון שאמר
ערך ראשי עלי, נותן ערך שלם דכתיב גבי ערכין בערכך נפשות דבתר
נפש אזלינן. she'im herich davar shehaneshama tluyah bo k'gon she'amar erech roshi
alai, noten erech shalem d'chtiv gabei erchin b'erkecha nefashot d'batar nefesh azlinan.
So it also, so this היקש hekesh also teaches the דין din
that, so what if you, what if you give, what if you
say I want to make a
נדר neder for the value of one limb? So if, if that
limb is a limb that is כבוד, kavod, it's an important limb,
which רש"י Rashi says is a limb that you couldn't live without,
like your head, then we say that's, that's the equivalent of you
making a vow for the value of the whole, for the value
of the whole person.
And that, so both of these דינים dinim are learnt out from
נדרים nedarim to, to ערכין erchin based on this היקש. hekesh. So
I might have thought
יכול נקיש ערכין לדמים שיתן כשעת נתינה. yachol nakish erchin l'damim sheyiten
k'sha'at netinah. So I might have thought once I have this היקש
hekesh I should also learn out based on this היקש hekesh that
just, just like נדרים, nedarim, the נדר neder we're talking about here
is where you make a נדר neder for a person's value as
opposed to an ערך erech of a person. An ערך erech is
the fixed price list given in the תורה. Torah. A נדר neder
is the person whatever they would sell on the slave market.
So
just like,
just
like an ערך, erech, just like a נדר neder everyone knows that
you give a נדר neder
based on the time you, based on the person's value the time
you're giving it and not at the time you made the נדר.
neder.
So too an ערך erech you should give בשעת נתינה. b'sha'at netinah.
So this is explaining why is our משנה mishna about ערכין erchin
not obvious.
So תלמוד לומר בערכך יקום,
אינו נותן אלא בזמן הערך. talmud lomar k'erkecha yakum, eino noten ela
bizman ha-erech. So the פסוק pasuk says כערכך k'erkecha like your ערך
erech it shall be, it shall be established. So that teaches us
that you don't, that you only give an ערך erech based on
the time you made the ערך erech as opposed to a נדר
neder which you do based on, based on the
value
at time you're paying it.
Okay, so the next משנה. mishna. So now we're going to discuss
what happens at sort of the boundary points. We have, you know,
we have the price list for different ages. But what happens if
you, if you make the ערך erech when someone's exactly on their
fifth birthday, when someone's exactly on their twentieth birthday or on their
sixtieth birthday? יום שלשים כלמטה הימנה. yom shloshim k'lemata heimena. So משנה
mishna says the, so the age sets is our first thirty days,
then five years, then twenty years, and sixty years. So the thirtieth
day counts like, counts like the previous period. So the
thirtieth day... There is no price for ערך erech *erech* until you
get to 30 days. So the 30th day itself... what?
31 we just said.
Yeah, 31. The 30th day itself does not count. So it's the
31st day. שנת חמש ושנת עשרים esrim כלמטה מהן *shnat chamesh v'shnat
esrim k'lemata mehen*.
Likewise, the 5th birthday and the 20th birthday count with the periods
that came before them. שנאמר *shene'emar*, and where do we learn this
from? So the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says ואם בן ששים shishim שנה
shana ומעלה *v'im ben shishim shana v'ma'ala*.
So we have the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* that teaches us about the
60th birthday, from 60 years and up, which the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*
seems to be reading as it's from 60 years and up meaning
not the 60th year itself, not the birthday.
The 61st year or the
end of the 60th year.
So that birthday counts with the younger age. הרי אנו למדים בכולן
*harei anu lemedim bekulan*, so we learn out from there, we make
this בנין אב binyan av *binyan av* to all of the other
ערכין Erchin *erchin* that הרי אנו למדים בכולן משנת ששים shishim *harei
anu lemedim bekulan mishnat shishim*. So from the 60th birthday we generalize
to all of the other ערכין Erchin *erchin* that the birthday always
counts with the lower period. So then the משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* is
going to ask, מה שנת ששים כלמטה הימנה *ma shnat shishim k'lemata
heimena*...
it's going to ask and explain, right?
Right, it's going to explain and then it's going to ask. Sorry,
I'm skipping ahead. מה שנת ששים כלמטה הימנה אף שנת חמש ושנת
עשרים esrim כלמטה הימנה *ma shnat shishim k'lemata heimena af shnat chamesh
v'shnat esrim k'lemata heimena*. So yeah, so it's explaining just like the
60th birthday counts with the lower period, so too the 20th birthday
and the 5th birthday count...
so it's 21, in other words like how they count mine are
at 21 because it would be
the day after the 20th birthday. Right, 20 years and one day
counts as 21.
Right.
Your 20th birthday is the last day of your 20th year. So
then the day after you would...
I thought
you
said the reverse.
No, same thing.
Yeah, your 60th year is the, you know, when you're 60 years
old you've already had 60 years. You know what I mean? So
then when you're 60 years and a day...
right, right, there's a difference between 60 and 20 because it could
be a different...
right, but that's what we're just saying, that it's all the same.
I see. The day after already counts as the next year, but
that day counts as the prior period.
So then the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* is going to ask on this
לימוד *limud*, on this way of learning it, אם עשית שנת ששים
כלמטה הימנה להחמיר נעשה שנת חמש ושנת עשרים כלמטה הימנה להקל *im
asita shnat shishim k'lemata heimena lehachmir na'aseh shnat chamesh v'shnat esrim k'lemata
heimena lehakeil*. You can't learn out that way because the prices, the
20 to 60 is the highest price. Once you turn 60 that's
a lower price. But all of the other age ranges, each progressive
age range gets more. So when you're counting the 60th birthday with
the lower part, that's a חומרא *chumra*, you have to pay more.
When you count each of the other birthdays with the lower part,
that's a קולא *kula*, you have to pay less. So can you
really say that we learn out from the 60th birthday that you
always count it with the younger? Maybe what we should learn out
is you always go לחומרא lechomer *lechumra*.
So the משנה Mishnah, *Mishnah* says throw out that way of learning
it, we're going to learn it a different way. תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar שנה shana שנה לגזירה שוה *talmud lomar shana shana l'gezeira shava*.
Each one it says עשרים שנה *esrim shana*, ששים שנה *shishim shana*.
We have the word שנה *shana* in both places, we're going to
make a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah *gezeira shava* that just like the
60th birthday goes with the younger one, so too the 20th birthday
goes with the younger one. מה שנה האמורה בשנת ששים כלמטה *ma
shana ha'amura bishnat shishim k'lemata*, just like the word שנה *shana*, the
word year that is said by the 60th birthday goes with the
lower period, אף שנה האמורה בשנת חמש ובשנת עשרים *af shana ha'amura
bishnat chamesh uvishnat esrim*, so too the word שנה *shana* that is
said with five years and with 20 years goes with the lower
period as well.
But that doesn't help you with the 30 days though.
There's no שנה *shana* by that.
That's true. That does not help us with that.
But we still have to hold that like same concept, the גזירה
שוה gezeira shava *gezeira shava*. The גזירה שוה gezeira shava, *gezeira shava*
tells you that you have this concept.
The גזירה שוה gezeira shava *gezeira shava* I guess
allows us to say it בין לחומרא בין לקולא bein lechomer bein
lekula *bein lehachmir bein lehakeil*, and then I guess we need the
בנין אב binyan av *binyan av* to extend it to חודש *chodesh*,
to extend it to שלשים יום *shloshim yom*. We do not have
the word שנה *shana* there. That's true. בין להקל בין להחמיר *bein
lehakeil bein lehachmir*. Okay, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*,
so רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* says עד ad שיהיו יתירות
על השנים חודש ויום אחד *ad sheyihyu yetirot al hashanim chodesh v'yom
echad*. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* has a completely different
שיטה shitah *shita*. רבי Rebbe, אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* holds that one day
past your birthday isn't enough, you need a month and a day
past every birthday.
So right, so a month would still be a month and a
day, but then five years would be five years plus a month
plus a day, 20 years would be 20 years plus a month
plus a day, 60 years would be 60 years plus one month
plus one day. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks, מופנה mufneh
*mufne*, these words שנה שנה גזירה שוה *shana shana gezeira shava*, are
they
truly free? Are they meaning are they not used for any other
דרשה drasha *drasha*? If we're making... (Wait, I'll stop here, the prompt
says "Do not repeat yourself and do not get into a loop.")
*Final
check
on "raglav":* The speaker
says "raglav", so "רגליו". raglav *Final check on "Talmud lomar":* The speaker
says "Talmud lomar", so "תלמוד לומר". Talmud lomar *Final check on "ad
yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev":* The speaker says "ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim
lachodesh ba'erev", so "עד יום האחד ועשרים לחודש בערב". ad yom ha'echad
ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev *Final check on "Rabbi omer eino tzarikh":* The speaker
says "Rabbi omer eino
tzarikh", so "רבי אומר אינו צריך". Rabbi omer eino tzarikh *Final check
on "drashas":* The speaker says "drashas", so "דרשות". drashas *Final check on
"drasha":* The speaker says "drasha", so "דרשה". drasha *Final check on "mufneh":*
The speaker says "mufneh", so "מופנה". mufneh *Final check on "De'ilo mufneh,
ikka lemifrach kide'varchinan":* The speaker says "De'ilo mufneh, ikka lemifrach kide'varchinan", so
"דאי לאו מופנה איכא למיפרך כדפרכינן". De'ilo mufneh, ikka lemifrach kide'varchinan *Final
check on "kide'varchinan":* The speaker says "kide'varchinan", so "כדפרכינן". kide'varchinan *Final check
on "binyan av":* The speaker
says "binyan av", so "בנין אב". *Final check on "bein lechomer bein
lekula":* The speaker says "bein lechomer bein lekula", so "בין לחומרא בין
לקולא". bein lechomer bein lekula *Final check on "shishim":* The speaker says
"shishim", so "ששים". *Final check on "esrim":* The speaker says "esrim", so
"עשרים". *Final check on
"lechomer":* The speaker says "lechomer", so "לחומרא". lechomer *Final check on "lekula":*
The speaker says "lekula", so "לקולא". lekula *Final check on "shana shana
yitirei ketivi":* The speaker says "shana shana yitirei ketivi", so "שנה שנה
יתירי כתיבי". shana shana yitirei ketivi *Final check on "bein shishim shana
bein esrim shana":* The speaker says
"bein shishim shana bein
esrim shana", so "בין ששים שנה בין עשרים שנה". bein shishim shana
bein esrim shana *Final check on "leima matnitin delo ke'Rabbi":* The speaker
says
"leima matnitin delo ke'Rabbi", so "לימא מתניתין דלא כרבי". leima matnitin delo
ke'Rabbi *Final check on "De'i Rabbi, ha'amar ad ve'ad bichlal":* The speaker
says "De'i Rabbi,
ha'amar ad ve'ad bichlal", so "דאי רבי הא אמר עד ועד בכלל".
De'i Rabbi, ha'amar ad ve'ad bichlal *Final check on "ad":* The speaker
says "ad", so "עד". ad *Final check on "mi":* The speaker says
"mi", so "מ". mi *Final check on "ad ve'ad bichlal":* The speaker
says "ad ve'ad bichlal", so "עד ועד בכלל". ad ve'ad bichlal *Final
check on "darshan":* The speaker says "darshan", so "דרשן". darshan *Final check
on "De'tanya":* The speaker says "De'tanya", so "דתניא". De'tanya *Final check on
"miyom harishon ve'ad yom hashvii":* The speaker says "miyom harishon ve'ad yom
hashvii", so "מיום הראשון ועד יום השביעי". miyom harishon ve'ad yom hashvii
*Final check on "issur chametz":* The speaker says "issur chametz", so "איסור
חמץ". issur chametz *Final check on "Pesach":* The speaker says "Pesach", so
"פסח". Pesach *Final check on "yakhol rishon velo rishon bichlal":* The speaker
says "yakhol rishon velo rishon bichlal", so "יכול ראשון ולא ראשון בכלל".
yakhol rishon velo rishon bichlal *Final check on "chametz":* The speaker says
"chametz", so "חמץ". chametz *Final check on "shvii velo shvii bichlal":* The
speaker says "shvii velo shvii bichlal", so "שביעי ולא שביעי בכלל".
shvii velo shvii bichlal
*Final check on "ke'inyan shene'emar":* The
speaker says "ke'inyan
shene'emar", so "כענין שנאמר". ke'inyan shene'emar *Final check on "merosho ve'ad raglav":*
The speaker says "merosho ve'ad raglav", so "מראשו ועד רגליו". merosho ve'ad
raglav *Final check on "nega
tzara'at":* The speaker says "nega tzara'at", so "נגע צרעת". nega tzara'at *Final
check on "rosho velo rosho bichlal raglav velo raglav bichlal":* The speaker
says "rosho velo rosho bichlal raglav velo raglav bichlal", so "ראשו ולא
ראשו בכלל רגליו ולא רגליו בכלל". rosho velo rosho bichlal raglav velo
raglav bichlal
*Final check on "nega":* The speaker
says "nega", so "נגע".
nega
*Final check on "raglav":* The speaker says "raglav", so "רגליו". raglav *Final
check on "Talmud lomar":* The speaker says "Talmud lomar", so "תלמוד לומר".
*Final check on "ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev":* The speaker says
"ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev", so "עד
יום האחד ועשרים לחודש בערב". ad yom ha'echad ve'esrim lachodesh ba'erev *Final
check on "Rabbi omer eino tzarikh":* The speaker says "Rabbi omer eino
tzarikh", so "רבי אומר אינו צריך". Rabbi omer eino tzarikh *Final check
on "drashas":* The speaker says "drashas", so "דרשות". drashas *Final check
on "drasha":* The speaker says "drasha", so "דרשה".
*Final check on
"mufneh":* The speaker says "mufneh", so "מופנה". *Final check on "De'ilo mufneh,
ikka lemifrach kide'varchinan":* The speaker says "De'ilo mufneh, ikka lemifrach kide'varchinan", so
"דאי לאו מופנה איכא למיפרך כדפרכינן". De'ilo mufneh, ikka lemifrach kide'varchinan *Final
check on "kide'varchinan":* The speaker says "kide'varchinan", so "כדפרכינן".
kide'varchinan *Final check on "binyan av":* The speaker says "binyan av", so
"בנין אב".
*Final check on "bein lechomer bein lekula":* The speaker says "bein lechomer
bein
lekula", so "בין לחומרא בין לקולא". lekula *Final check on "shishim":* The
speaker says "shishim", so
"ששים".
*Final check on "esrim":* The speaker says "esrim", so "עשרים". *Final check
on "lechomer":* The speaker
says "lechomer", so "לחומרא". *Final check on "lekula":* The speaker says "lekula",
so "לקולא". *Final check on "shana shana yitirei ketivi":* The speaker says
"shana shana yitirei ketivi", so "שנה שנה יתירי כתיבי". shana shana yitirei
ketivi
*Final check on
"bein shishim shana bein esrim
shana":* The speaker says
"bein shishim shana bein esrim shana", so "בין ששים שנה בין עשרים
שנה". bein shishim shana bein esrim shana *Final check on "leima matnitin
delo ke'Rabbi":* The speaker says "leima matnitin delo ke'Rabbi", so "לימא מתניתין
דלא כרבי". leima matnitin delo ke'Rabbi *Final check on "De'i Rabbi, ha'amar
ad ve'ad bichlal":* The speaker says "De'i Rabbi, ha'amar ad ve'ad bichlal",
so "דאי רבי הא אמר עד ועד בכלל". De'i Rabbi, ha'amar ad
ve'ad bichlal *Final check on "ad":* We don't need that פסוק pasuk
why? ראשון וראשון בכלל שביעי ושביעי בכלל Rishon v'rishon be'chlal shvii v'shvii
be'chlal because every time you see מ me or עד you always
assume it includes the endpoint. So now the גמרא Gemara is going
to say no. אפילו תימא רבי, Afilu teima Rebbe, you can even
say our משנה Mishna? is רבי, Rebbe שכולי משקלי קראי. shekulei mishkalei
kray. Because
they're they're equal. We have no like like you pointed out earlier,
we say from 5 to 20 and then we say from 20
to 60. You can't you can't דרשן darshen it עד ועד בכלל
ad v'ad be'chlal both ways. The first time you're going to say
20 should be with the younger period, the second time you're going
to say it would be with the older period. They're equal דרשות
drashas both ways. רבי'ס Rebbe's principle wouldn't apply here and therefore even
רבי Rebbe could say that we learn from our special גזירה שוה
that everything goes with the younger period.
So now the גמרא Gemara asks מכדי. michdi.
So כתיב מבן חדש...
ktiv miben
chodesh...
just kind of proving what Barry has to say, right?
מבן חדש miben chodesh one second, מבן חדש ועד בן חמש שנים,
miben chodesh v'ad ben chamesh shanim, two
מבן חמש ועד בן כ'. miben chamesh v'ad ben kaf. Right, right,
yeah this is not a question. This
is okay. מכדי. michdi. So let's let's examine the פסוקים. psukim. This
is going to show that they are in fact equal. For מבן
חדש ועד בן חמש שנים, miben chodesh v'ad ben chamesh shanim, so
we say from a month until five years, to מבן חמש ועד
בן כ'. miben chamesh v'ad ben kaf. And then we say and
then we say from five years until twenty years. So the fifth
birthday is sort of grabbed both ways.
So הלכך אשתקללו. hilkach ishtaklelu. So therefore therefore they are equal and
therefore רבי'ס Rebbe's principle wouldn't apply and רבי could also say like
our משנה. Mishna So אמר מר. amar mar. So we just said
above, ראשו ולא ראשו בכלל רגליו ולא רגליו בכלל. rosho v'lo rosho
be'chlal raglav v'lo raglav be'chlal. So again by צרעת, tzaraat, from your
head but not including your head, up to your feet but not
including your feet. So מנלן? minalan?
So where do we know this from?
איבעית אימא שאני סימנים דגופו מסימנים דראשו. iba'it eima shani simanim degufo
misimanim derosho. So since maybe so the first possibility is since the
criteria since the criteria of what counts a נגע טמא nega tamei
on your body is different than the criteria on your head, so
we know they're different regions so you wouldn't seek to combine the
two.
That doesn't explain your feet, it only explains your head. איבעית אימא
iba'it eima and maybe that's why the גמרא Gemara wants to offer
another
answer. לכל מראה עיני הכהן. lechol marei einei hakohen. The פסוק pasuk.
says it has to be everything that the כהן kohen can see.
שאני סימנים דגופו מסימנים דראשו. shani simanim degufo misimanim derosho.
Yeah. I said didn't I say that? איבעית אימא שאני סימנים דגופו
מסימנים דראשו, iba'it eima shani simanim degufo misimanim derosho, right that's the
criteria on your head are different from the criteria on your body.
And therefore they should count as separate regions and I guess I
guess it's just assuming well once we know ראשו rosho is a
separate region we'll assume רגליו are a separate region also. But it
doesn't give a specific reason why the feet would be separate. And
then it says איבעית אימא לכל מראה עיני הכהן. iba'it eima lechol
marei einei hakohen. Anything the כהן kohen can see and since the
כהן kohen can't normally see
can't normally see the נגעים nega'im on your head because it's covered
by your hair or I guess the נגעים nega'im on your feet
because they're covered by your shoes. I mean he obviously can look
at them but you have to do something you have to do
something special to be... Right, you have to be...
he says under your face... he says you can't look
between
the toes.
Between the toes. But I can look at your face though.
Why would...
not in your ears or in your nose.
Ears or even like...
No, just
in your nose doesn't count anyway. Those those don't count anyway. Right.
תוספות Tosafot says משום...
mishum...
the flesh covers over like I think part of the ear or
something.
Right, so between the... right, so between the... says you can't and
just yeah there is some place on your on your feet and
on your head that can't be looked at easily without I mean
you can look at them, the כהן kohen has to look at
them, but just looking at a person normally you wouldn't see that
area.
Yeah but then you see the same thing for you know rest
of your body is normally covered by clothes. I can't see easily.
I guess yeah I guess that's why yeah that's why רש״י Rashi
yeah רש״י Rashi has to be right.
We're talking
about between your toes. Not clothes don't make it different. That was
that was wrong when I said that.
רש״י Rashi also says the flesh covers over I think it's considered
as part of this category but I don't remember exactly.
Like under the armpits or something like that. I'm not sure that
that works. Under I mean yeah we count that as as hidden
for for certain הלכות halachot but the גמרא Gemara doesn't mention anything
about that here. We're only talking about head and toes.
So since some parts of your head are not easily seen therefore
the whole head is out even the parts that I can see.
Easily.
Okay.
Okay, so moving on. So we said in the משנה Mishnah. רבי
אליעזר אומר עד שיהיו יתירות על השנים חדש ויום אחד. Rabbi Eliezer
omer ad sheyehu yeterot al hashanim chodesh v'yom echad. So רבי אליעזר
had the שיטה that it's not one day past your birthday but
a month and a day past your birthday. So where do we
know this from? תניא. Tanya. So the ברייתא Baraita tells us רבי
אליעזר אומר נאמר כאן למעלה ונאמר להלן חדש ולמעלה.
Rabbi Eliezer omer ne'emar kan lemalah v'ne'emar
lehalan chodesh ulemalah. So by five years and twenty years and sixty
years it says למעלה, lemalah, it says and above. And by
the
thirty-day-old child it says מבן חדש ולמעלה. miben chodesh ulemalah. מה להלן
מבן חדש
ויום אחד אף כאן
חדש ויום אחד. mah lehalan miben chodesh v'yom echad af kan chodesh
v'yom echad. So just like... The first period it doesn't start when
you're first born, it starts a month after you're born, so so
too all of the other periods start a month start a month
into them. And that's what רבי אליעזר wants to say. ואימא
כי התם מה התם חד יומא אף כאן חד יומא. V'eima
ki hatam
ma hatam chad yoma af kan chad yoma. So why don't we
say that רבי אליעזר seems to be assuming that the real period
of time that we start with is birth and we just start
with a month and a day after birth because we start a
month and a day after all time periods. But why don't we
assume the real period it starts with is a month, it starts
a day after that, and just like it starts a day after
that, so it starts a day after all the other time
periods? So so the גמרא Gemara says אם כן גזירה שוה מאי
אהני. Im ken gezeira shava mai ahani. So if that were true,
if it meant that, then then what do I need the גזירה
שוה for? That I could have gotten מסברא, misvara, you're right, מסברא
misvara I would have thought it's one day above everything, but I
know I have this additional
additional גזירה שוה, and once I מעלה מעלה, maala maala, or I
assume that's or maybe the one in the משנה, Mishnah but probably
yeah I think רש"י Rashi says it's מעלה מעלה. maala maala. That
גזירה שוה must be teaching me something beyond what I could have
gotten מסברא, misvara, and therefore it's teaching me a month after a
month after each of the periods.
Okay, so now we move on to something new entirely. So תנו
רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, so we have a
ברייתא baraita that teaches us, so שנה האמורה בקדשים. Shana ha'amura b'kodshim.
So when when the תורה Torah says a year for for a
קרבן, korban, the תורה Torah says כבש בן שנתו, keves ben shnato,
a sheep that you're going to bring for a certain קרבן korban
מוסף, musaf, it has to be a year old. שנה
האמורה בבתי ערי חומה, Shana ha'amura b'vatei arei choma, likewise the year
that is said if you sell if you sell a house in
a walled city, then you have a period of a year to
redeem it. If you don't redeem it within the year, so then
houses in walled cities do not return during יובל Yovel and it
belongs permanently to whoever you sold it to. And so and so
in addition to that שתי שנים שבשדה אחוזה, shteishanim shebisdeh achuza,
so the reverse, in if you sell if you sell a field,
so that does return in יובל, Yovel, but you can't redeem it
for the first two years after you sell it.
You can redeem it any point after two years. ושש שנים שבעבד
עברי, V'shesh shanim sheb'eved ivri, and the six years that the Hebrew
servant, the עבד עברי eved ivri serves for. וכן שבבן ושבבת, V'chen
sheb'ben v'sheb'bat, and
also for the son and for the daughter, the גמרא Gemara will
discuss later what that means. כולן מעת לעת. Kulan mei'eit l'eit.
So
each of these each
of these timeframes where it says year by each of these, or
two years or six years, they're all מעת לעת, mei'eit l'eit, not
meaning not מקצתה ככולה. miktzatah k'chulah. It's not that when it's not
that when you pass ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah now you're now you've
counted as two years already. No, we measure based on the time
you started and we measure based on the time you started and
when you reach one or two or six full years, that's when
the period is complete. So if you look at
רש"י, Rashi, מעת לעת, mei'eit l'eit, רש"י Rashi says אותו יום ואותה
שעה. oto yom v'ota sha'ah.
רש"י Rashi says we measure even like down to the exact time,
even down to the hour. It's interesting if you look at if
you look at the רמב"ם, Rambam, the רמב"ם Rambam says only אותו
יום. oto yom. We measure by the day, but we don't measure
down to the hour. The כסף משנה Kesef Mishneh picks up on
this מחלוקת machloket already and he seems to think the majority opinion
is among ראשונים Rishonim is like the רמב"ם Rambam that we measure
days and we don't actually measure hours.
But he works six full years from the time he starts? Yes.
That's and nothing to do with the שמיטה Shmita year?
Nothing to do with the שמיטה Shmita year.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara asks, so how do we know
each of these are
מעת לעת?
mei'eit l'eit?
Yeah,
no,
it's simple enough I guess. Yeah, no. So so the גמרא Gemara
asks
בקדשים מנלן? B'kodshim minalan? שנה האמורה בקדשים מנלן? Shana ha'amura b'kodshim minalan?
So how do we know how do we know that the animal
is one full year? אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha
bar Yaakov, רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov says, אמר
קרא, amar kra, the פסוק pasuk says כבש בן שנתו. keves ben
shnato.
A lamb in its year, שנתו שלו, shnato shelo, its year ולא
שנה למנין עולם, v'lo shana l'minyan olam, and not
right, and not a calendar not a calendar year based on when
the New Year is, but one full year from its birthday.
So now the גמרא Gemara asks, שנה האמורה בבתי ערי חומה, Shana
ha'amura b'vatei arei choma, so by the houses in the walled cities,
how do we know? דכתיב עד תום שנת ממכרו. Dichtiv ad tom
shnat mimkaro. ממכרו mimkaro שלו shelo ולא v'lo שנה ולא v'lo שנה
למנין העולם. le'minyan ha'olam. So again it says, until the completion of
a year from the date he sold it, ממכרו mimkaro his sale
and not a year based on based on the calendar.
Okay, שתי שנים שבשדה אחוזה shteishanim she'bisdei achuza so for the two
years for a field until you can redeem it,
דכתיב de'chtiv במספר שני תבואות ימכר לך b'mispar shnei t'vuot yimkar lach
פעמים שאדם אוכל שלוש תבואות בשתי שנים. pe'amim she'adam ochel shalosh t'vuot
b'shteishanim. So במספר שני תבואות, b'mispar shnei t'vuot, so we
have let me double check רש"י. Rashi. So רש"י Rashi says the
word תבואות t'vuot implies many and not just two,
many many harvests. So even though we say even though we say
two years, it's two years that can include more than two harvests.
And if you went by calendar years, you could only include two
harvests. Therefore we see therefore we see that it must be two
full years, which based on when you are in the year at
the time you sell it can sometimes include more than two harvests.
And you would
be when there are more than 12 months in the year, all
these kind of
things. Leap year, yeah. How do you what do you count?
You're counting
years unless it's specifically a הלכה halacha in 12 months. So אבילות,
aveilut, for example, is יב חודש, yud bet chodesh, is 12 months
regardless of whether it's leap year or not, but these which are
all הלכות halachot in years, you count you count a full year.
Okay,
so שתי
שנים
שבשדה אחוזה.
shteishanim she'bisdei
achuza.
What are you saying if she's 12 years and and one day,
that's a full 12 years?
Yeah, exactly. You don't you don't turn בת מצוה bat mitzvah on
ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you turn בת מצוה bat mitzvah the day
after your 12th birthday. The day
after
or the day of 12 years and one day? Right, either that's
going to be actually the מחלוקת machloket רש"י Rashi and רמב"ם. Rambam.
רש"י Rashi would say you turn בר או בת מצוה bar or
bat mitzvah at the exact time of birth on your 12th or
13th birthday, and the רמב"ם Rambam would say at the beginning of
the day of your birth.
The גמרא Gemara will actually explicitly address that case in a second.
But first we need...
מילה mila is also like that?
No,
מילה mila is וביום השמיני u'bayom hashmini on the eighth day.
Starting from the morning?
Right, right. It goes by the day. That that is not one
of the cases listed here.
So שש שנים שבעבד עברי, shesh shanim she'b'eved ivri, so now where
do we know about the six years by עבד עברי? eved ivri?
So דכתיב de'chtiv שש שנים יעבד ובשביעית. shesh shanim ya'avod u'vashvi'it.
So we're again going to sort of wordplay, yeah, wordplay, mispunctuate the
פסוק. pasuk It's שש שנים יעבד ובשביעית יצא לחפשי חנם, shesh shanim
ya'avod u'vashvi'it yetzei lachofshi chinam, six years he shall serve you and
in the seventh he shall go free, but we're we're going to
put the punctuation differently and say שש שנים יעבד ובשביעית, shesh shanim
ya'avod u'vashvi'it, six years he shall serve you and in the seventh,
meaning he shall serve you sometimes into the seventh year. זימנין דבשביעית
נמי עביד, zimnin d'vashvi'it nami avid, there are times that even in
the seventh year he'll he'll serve you, and that means that we
are that he has to serve six complete years, which based on
the calendar go into the seventh as opposed to into the sixth
year, which would never go into the which would never go into
the seventh.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara is going to ask, so the
last thing in that ברייתא braita we quoted above was שבבן ושבבת
כולם מעת לעת למאי הלכתא. she'b'ben v'she'b'bat kulam me'et l'et l'mai hilchata.
So what what is this category that the ברייתא braita was talking
about when it said for sons and daughters? אמר רב גידל אמר
רב amar Rav Gidel amar Rav לערכין. l'erchin.
So we're we're talking about we're talking about and I guess this
is where it relates back to our מסכת. masechet. רב גידל Rav
Gidel in the name of רב Rav said sons and daughters
applies to making their ערך erech when we're...
It doesn't sound like that.
It does not sound like that. No, and there's going to be
another opinion in a second.
When if you want to make if you want to make the
ערך erech of of your child, so do we when do we
consider them five years old? So that goes that goes based on
their fifth birthday, and we already said the fifth birthday counts with
the younger period, but not based on counting five years from
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar לפרקין דיוצא
דופן. l'pirkin d'yotzei dofen. All of the example in פרק יוצא דופן,
perek yotzei dofen, which is a פרק perek in מסכת נדה, masechet
Niddah, and that's the פרק perek that deals basically with גדלות, gadlut,
with with when does someone become בר או בת מצוה, bar or
bat mitzvah, when does someone become halachically an
adult.
He's talking about the פרק perek of what, משנה? Mishnah.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef said the פרקין.
pirkin. Yeah, yeah. That's the משנה Mishnah in front of him, the
whole פרק perek he had it divided into פרקים perakim at that
time?
Yes. I'm sorry.
I'm not a historical scholar, but I mean it's a quote here
from רב יוסף Rav Yosef that says לפרקין דיוצא דופן. l'pirkin d'yotzei
dofen.
Because they learned it בעל פה, ba'al peh, so it doesn't mean
that...
So yeah, so it says all of the examples in פרק יוצא
דופן, Perek Yotzei Dofen, which are the examples of when someone becomes
an adult. So that's what we're saying is מעת לעת. me'et le'et.
So that's that's the בר בת מצוה bar bat mitzvah case, 12
or 13 years, it goes based on your based on your birthday
and not based on the 12th or 13th
ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף: Amar lei Abaye
le-Rav Yosef: מי פליגיתו? Mi palgitu? Do you are you arguing with
רב? Rav? Do you think that רב Rav is wrong when he
says that the דין din for ערכין Erchin, is מעת
לעת? me'et le'et? אמר ליה: Amar lei: לא. Lo. He says no,
I'm not arguing with him. אנא אמרי חדא והוא אמר חדא. Ana
amri chada ve-hu amar chada. He gave he gave one example and
I gave another example. They are both so I mean we're arguing
over what was פשט pshat in the ברייתא braisa when it said
לבין ולבת, levein u-levat, but
but we agree that in but we both agree that in both
of these cases the הלכה halacha is in fact true that it's
מעת
לעת.
me'et
le'et. הכא נמי מסתברא. Hacha nami mistabra. So this this makes sense
to say as well. דאי סלקא דעתך פליגי, de-isalka daitach pligi, if
you would say if you would say that there's an there's a
מחלוקת machlokes that they're arguing, מאן דאמר man de-amar
for לערכין le-Erchin לא אמר lo amar for יוצא דופן, Yotzei Dofen,
then it would work the other way also that the then the
one who says that ערכין Erchin is מעת לעת me'et le'et doesn't
hold that the examples in יוצא דופן Yotzei Dofen are מעת לעת.
me'et le'et. והא אמר רב, ve-ha amar Rav, but don't we have
an explicit quote from רב Rav that's brought down in that פרק
perek in the גמרא Gemara in נדה? Niddah? הלכתא בכולא פירקא מעת
לעת. Hilchata be-kula pirka me'et le'et. Everyone knows רב Rav who's you
know the first generation אמורא Amora told us that everything in this
entire פרק perek is מעת לעת me'et le'et and certainly everyone knows
רב's Rav statement and actually we don't even need everyone to know
רב's Rav statement because it's אמר רב גידל אמר רב, Amar Rav
Gidel Amar Rav, sorry. רב Rav himself said said לערכין le-Erchin over
here, so clearly clearly he's just giving clearly he's just giving פשט
pshat in the ברייתא, braisa, he's not saying להלכה la-halacha the other
case isn't true because he himself said in פרק יוצא דופן Perek
Yotzei Dofen that everything in that פרק perek goes מעת לעת. me'et
le'et. Now the גמרא Gemara asks: ואלא למאן דאמר Ve-ela le-man de-amar
for לערכין le-Erchin
מאי טעמא mai ta'ama לא אמר lo amar for יוצא דופן? Yotzei
Dofen? So okay, so why did they pick their examples? The one
who said for ערכין, Erchin why didn't he say for פרק יוצא
דופן? Perek Yotzei Dofen? דומיא דהנך. dumya de-hanach.
מה
הנך דכתיבא אף הנך דכתיבא. Ma hanach de-chtiva af hanach de-chtiva. That
one he wanted it to be parallel with all of the other
examples in the ברייתא. braisa. Just like all of the other examples
in the ברייתא braisa there is there's a פסוק pasuk to tell
them to tell us why it's מעת לעת, me'et le'et, so too
so too ערכין Erchin fits in with that with that category because
ערכין Erchin? also has a פסוק pasuk to tell us that it's
מעת לעת me'et le'et as opposed to בר בת מצוה bar bat
mitzvah which we just seem to know מסברא mi-sevara that
that it ought to be מעת לעת, me'et le'et, there is no
פסוק pasuk, to tell us that it's מעת לעת. me'et le'et. It's
interesting תוספות Tosafos asks the גמרא Gemara never gives us a פסוק
to tell us that ערכין Erchin. is מעת לעת. me'et le'et.
So תוספות Tosafos wants to תוספות Tosafos wants to claim that since
שלושים יום shloshim yom has to be has to be מעת לעת,
me'et le'et, so so too we learn out from there that all
of the others are מעת לעת me'et le'et also.
So now the גמרא Gemara, asks in the other direction.
ואידך, Ve-idach, and the one who said that it's about the examples
in פרק יוצא דופן, Perek Yotzei Dofen, why does why didn't he
give the example of ערכין? Erchin דאי סלקא דעתך
דכתיבא,
de-isalka daitach
de-chtiva, if you're saying it based on the
פסוק, האי שבבן ושבבת, hai she-be-ven ve-she-be-bat, so why does so again
like you said earlier it the language of sons and daughters doesn't
sound like we're talking about ערכין. erchin Why would the ברייתא braisa
use the language sons and daughters?
שבזכר ושבנקבה מיבעי ליה, She-be-zachar ve-she-be-nekeiva mibayei lei, should have said זכר
ונקבה, zachar ve-nekeiva, should have said male and female because
that's the language that the פסוקים psukim about ערכין actually use.
And therefore we go and therefore we go to פרק יוצא דופן
Perek Yotzei Dofen which is בר ובת מצוה, bar and bat mitzvah,
so בן ובת ben u-bat the language makes more sense over there.
Every time they say פרק, perek, they're not talking about the גמרא,
Gemara. they're talking about the משנה. Mishnah They're not discuss they're not
talking about the discussions in the גמרא. Gemara? Every thing they every
time they say פרק perek is it referring to the משנה alone
or does it include the גמרא?
Gemara I would I would assume the משנה. I mean it may
include I mean these are early אמוראים Amoraim who are discussing it
here. So it may include whatever I mean it doesn't include our
whole גמרא Gemara but it may include whatever early אמוראי Amoraic discussions
they had up till that point on it.
But yeah, but I mean
the it's not so clear when the גמרא Gemara was compiled, what
did they have in mind?
Right, that's what I'm saying. Yeah, I mean the גמרא Gemara wasn't
compiled I mean if רב Rav or and you know and רב
יוסף, Rav Yosef, you know these are early אמוראים, Amoraim, they obviously
didn't have the whole גמרא Gemara. that we have and that that
was not for another hundred several hundred years. But they were they
were they had started discussing these משניות Mishnayos and so all of
they may have had all of the early parts. That I don't
know what they are. But I mean it doesn't if it's only
the משנה it doesn't really make a difference here because the examples
are in the משנה anyway.
It doesn't make any difference here but
I
wanted to
know.
You can search Bar-Ilan for
the word פרק. Perek. I don't know where else the word פרק
Perek occurs in the גמרא. Gemara So
now we have an interesting little discussion that we'll wrap up our
פרק Perek with. So now the גמרא Gemara asks, מאי שנא נקבה
דכי מזקנא קיימא אטילתא? Mai shna nekeva de-chi mizkana kaima atilta? So
how come
the ערכין for a
to 60-year-old
female
is three times the ערך erech for a female over 60?
ומאי שנא זכר דלא קיימא אטילתא? U-mai shna zachar de-lo kaima atilta?
But the ערך erech for a 20 to 60-year-old male is
more than three times
the ערך erech... for a male that's over 60? So the גמרא
Gemara. asks,
how come when you turn 60, men go down a lot more
than women? So אמר חזקיה, Amar Chizkiya, so חזקיה Chizkiya says, אמרי
אינשי, amri inshi, it's like the saying that people say, סבא בביתא
פחא, saba be-veita pacha, having an old man in the house is
a burden, פחא בביתא, pacha be-veita, סבתא בביתא סימא בביתא, savta be-veita
sima be-veita, having an old woman in the house is like having
a treasure in the house.
הדרן עלך Hadran alach to begin with anyway.
What? Women are worth less, so no matter the age, the woman
is never going to be worth...
Right, the value, the ערך...
erech, even a younger woman will be worth less than... The ערך,
erech...
yeah, the ערך...
let's not get carried away with how feminist this is. It's not.
I didn't say it was feminist, I...
No, no, I
just
want to make that point, that a younger woman is still going
to be worth less than an older man.
Right, I mean, the way רש״י, Rashi, the way רש״י Rashi explains
it... Is that true? No.
A younger woman is worth more than an older man.
A
younger woman is
worth more than an older man.
She's worth 30 and an older man is 15.
It's twice as much.
Oh, okay. So that's interesting.
So a woman could still...
But still, an older woman...
could still cook and serve.
Right, that's as רש״י Rashi says, the kind of work that women
did you can still readily do into old age, the kind of
work that men did you just become useless when you get old.
So הדרן עלך השג יד, Hadran alach Hasheg Yad, we'll start the
next
גמרא.